A Finding Aid to the Jan Butterfield Papers, 1950-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.buttjan
Archives of American Art
- Interviews and Lectures, 1959-1997; Series 1; 4.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-5
  - Robert Irwin, 1975 June; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Article #4, placing your attention on the periphery of knowing" (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Robert Irwin, 1975 August; 3 Sound cassettes Duplicates; 1 sound tape reels Original; box label reads "latest article" (Box 3, Item 5)
    Side 1 of duplicate cassette 1 of 3 contains approximately 8 min., 30 seconds of Irwin interview not found on original reel. Duplicate cassette 2 of 3 (labeled "side 2 1/2") contains an additional lecture and Q&A with an unidentified male speaker, approximately 41 minutes in duration.
  - Robert Irwin, 1975 December; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Telephone call, Irwin conversation re: 'placing your attention' final OK" (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Robert Irwin, 1976; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Hegel, Marx, Kierkegaard, also Whitney show discussion" (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Robert Irwin, Lecture, "Artist As Educator," Berkeley Museum, 1976 May 5 (Box 3)
    See box 4, item 19; Hap Tivey, Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 October
  - Robert Irwin, 1976 May 12 (Box 3)
    See box 5, folder 3; Panel Discussions, Space and Place, UCLA
  - Robert Irwin, 1977 June 2; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Telephone conv. re: Whitney show" (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Robert Irwin, 1977 July 5-6; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Robert Irwin, 1977 August 3; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Telephone conversation re: editing of article #5" (Box 3, Item 10)
  - Robert Irwin, Interview fragment, circa 1977 (Box 3)
    See box 1, item 21; Robert Colescott, 1979 February 1
  - Robert Irwin, Lecture, Berkeley Museum Series, 1978 April 20; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "At time of 'Space As Support' exhibition, excellent ocndensation of theories" (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Robert Irwin, 1979 May 26; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Discussion re: premis of light and space book" (Box 3, Item 12)
  - Robert Irwin, 1980 July 15; 1 sound tape reels Box label reads "Newest work, book discussion L&S" (Box 3, Item 13)
  - Robert Irwin, 1984; 2 Sound cassettes Originals; 2 Sound cassettes Duplicates (Box 3, Item 14)
    Sequence of interview is cassette 1 of 2, unlabeled side, then side marked "84"; cassette 2 of 2, side marked 3, then side marked 2.
  - Robert Irwin, 1987 March; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 15)
    Only side 1 of cassette 1 of 2 contains the interview from March, 1987. Brief and unrelated recordings exist on cassette 1, side 2, and cassette 2, side 1.
  - Oliver Jackson, 1982 August; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 16)
  - Craig Kaufman, 1976 February 6; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 17)
  - Jim Love, 1973 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 18)
  - Tom Marioni Lecture, Indianapolis Museum, 1975 January; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 19)
  - Fred Martin, 1980 November 5; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 20)
    Original box labeled "blank," but reel is not blank.
  - Marshall McLuhan, Southern Methodist University, 1973 November 30; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 21)
  - Blanche McVeigh and the Fort Worth Circle (Box 3)
    See box 4, item 25; Richard Tuttle, Lecture in Dallas, Texas, circa 1971
  - Jack Mims, 1973; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 22)
  - Robert Misrach (Box 3)
    See box 1, item 2; Lita Albuquerque and Richard Misrach interview with unidentified curators at California State University at Fullerton, 1988
  - John Mason, 1978 July 28; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 23)
  - William Moritz (Box 3)
  - Ed Moses, 1976; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 24)
  - Ed Moses, Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 November; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 25)
  - Stephen Nagourney, P.S. 1, 1981 August; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 26)
  - Bruce Nauman, 1974 May 29; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 27)
  - Bruce Nauman, circa 1975; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 28)
  - Bruce Nauman, 1976 June 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 29)
  - Bruce Nauman, 1981 March; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 30)
  - Manuel Neri, 1976 December; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 31)
  - Manuel Neri, 1980 December 18; 1 sound tape reels Original box labeled: "Art and the Spirit" (Box 3, Item 32)
  - Louise Nevelson Lecture, Berkeley, Calif., circa 1975; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 33)
  - Maria Nordman, 1978 April; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 34)
  - Maria Nordman, 1979 June 11; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 35)
  - Maria Nordman, 1979 June; 1 sound tape reels Original box labeled "Interview # III" (Box 3, Item 36)
    Different from June 11, 1979 recording.
  - Eric Orr, 1979 February 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 37)
  - Eric Orr, 1980 October; 1 sound tape reels (Box 3, Item 38)
  - Eric Orr, 1981 August; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 1)
  - Beverly Pepper, 1975 February 10; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 2)
  - Beverly Pepper, 1975 May 20; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 3)
    Pepper interview is found in the middle of side 1 of reel. Reel also contains multiple partially taped-over recordings, including notes dictated by Butterfield regarding archival research at the beginning of side 1, a 2 min. fragment of an interview with Richard Arneson of October 1974 at the end of side 1, and a fragement of a forum on post-minimalist art in the middle of side 2.
  - Ken Price, 1978 July; 2 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 3)
  - Joseph Raffael, 1976 July 15; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Milton Resnick, with Pat Passlof, circa 1970; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 5)
    Original cassette 1 of 2 also labeled "Dennis Hopper," but Dennis Hopper is not in recording.
    Cassette 2 of 2 also contains a conversation with unidentified men, possibly instructors at the Northwood Experimental Art Institute in Dallas, TX, and two fragments from unidentified acoustiguide recordings.
  - Milton Resnick, 1971 February 20; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 6)
    Interview conducted by unidentified man, possibly Henry Hopkins.
  - Sam Richardson, 1978 May; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Sam Richardson, 1982 September; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 8)
  - Jim Roche, The Believable Literalism and Sure Fire Presentation; Here We Are Henry Piece, circa 1972; 1 Sound cassettes Original cassette also labeled "Jim Roche personal tape piece" and "1. Relation symbols, 2. Wiritings on wall" (Box 4, Item 9)
  - Jim Roche, 1973; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 10)
    Cassette 2 of 2 marked "January" but seems to follow cassette marked "spring"
  - Ed Ruscha, circa 1981; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 11)
  - Ursula Schneider, interview conducted by Lorri Surrihan, circa 1973; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 12)
  - Richard Serra (Box 4)
    See also box 5, folder 2; Panel Discussions, Space and Place, UCLA
  - Richard Shaw, 1981 July; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 13)
  - Hassel Smith, circa 1974; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 14)
    Interview is on first 32 minutes of side 1 and last 13 minutes of side 2. Remainder of interview is taped over with a conversation among Smith, Carlos Villa, and Butterfield about the San Francisco Art Institute.
  - Hassel Smith, 1977; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 15)
  - Joan Tewkesbury Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1976 October; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 16)
  - Wayne Thiebaud, 1976 July 4; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 17)
  - Hap Tivey, Interdisciplinary Seminar and Interview, San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 October; 2 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 18)
    Interview begins approximately 12 minutes into reel 1, side 2. Reel 2, side 2 also contains fragments of a recording of a 1974 meeting of Advocates for the Arts, and a slide talk by an unidentified artist, possibly Laddie John Dill.
    Original box for reel 2 of 2 also labeled with names Robert Irwin, Judy Chicago, and Dennis O'Leary, but these individuals are not found in the recording.
  - Hap Tivey, Lecture, San Francisco Art Institute, 1977 October; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 19)
    Side 2 of reel contians Robert Irwin Lecture, "The Artist as Educator," Berkeley Museum, May 5 1976.
  - Hap Tivey, 1979 February13; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 20)
  - Hap Tivey, 1986; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 21)
  - Garner Tullis, 1981 November; 2 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on cassette 1 of 2: "Sam Francis work" (Box 4, Item 22)
  - James Turrell, 1979 June 16; 2 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 23)
  - James Turrell, 1981 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 24)
  - Richard Tuttle, Lecture in Dallas, Texas, circa 1971; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 25)
    Side 2 contains a recorded conversation between Butterfield and an unidentified man and woman concerning printmaker Blanche McVeigh and the Fort Worth Circle.
  - Dewain Valentine, circa 1978; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on cassette: "first interview" (Box 4, Item 26)
  - Dewain Valentine, 1979 October; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 27)
    Original box also labeled "Sam Francis 6/22/79," and "no! blank - but keep above info: S.F. tape may be missing." Reel contains only the Valentine interview of October 1979.
  - Carlos Villa, 1978 March 4; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 28)
    See also box 4, item 14; Hassel Smith, circa 1974, for a conversation between Smith, Villa and Butterfield regarding the San Francisco Art Institute.
  - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1981 June; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 29)
  - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1982 March 16; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 30)
    Handwritten notes on original cassette read "Side #3?" and "side#4?", but no sides 1 and 2 for this interview are found in the collection.
  - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1984 August; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 31)
  - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1987 October; 3 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 4, Item 32)
  - Robert Wade, 1973; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 33)
  - Doug Wheeler, 1979 July 15; 2 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 34)
  - Doug Wheeler, 1981 March; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 35)
  - Ed Wortz (Box 4)
  - Michael Yost, Project Manager for Roden Crater, 1979 December 6; 1 Sound cassettes Poor sound quality (Box 4, Item 36)
  - Michael Yost, Project Manager for Roden Crater, 1980 May; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 37)
    Original reel also contains part of an oral history conducted by Jan Butterfield for the Archives of American Art. Reel has been removed from the collection and stored with the oral history collection. A digital copy of the Yost interview is available for research access.
  - Elyn Zimmerman, 1979 August; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Item 38)
  - Unidentified Artist, Question and Answer Discussion, circa 1959-1997; 1 Sound cassettes Handwritten note on label: "OK to erase" (Box 4, Item 39)
  - Unidentified Artist, Class visit, circa 1959-1997; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 40)
    Class visit found in first 13 minutes of recording. Cassette also contains an unidentified literary reading, music, and fragments of an acoustiguide for a Van Gogh exhibition at LACMA.
  - Unidentified Curators, Fort Worth Museum of Science and History, circa 1959-1997; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 41)
  - Unidentified Lecture on Light and Space Art in Antiquity, circa 1995; 2 Sound cassettes Handwritten on both cassette cases: "Cutting Edge, 10/7" (Box 4, Item 42)
  - Panel Discussions (Box 5)
    - The Influence of Modern Painting on Our Tradition, University of Southern Illinois, with Milton Resnick and Edward Dugmore, 1959; 1 sound tape reels 7 inch (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Attack, Milton Resnick and Ad Reinhardt Debate, The Club, 1961 January 1; 1 sound tape reels 7 inch (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Space and Place, University of California Los Angeles (Box 5)
      - Hap Tivey, Mowry Baden, Ed Wortz, 1976 April 7; 1 sound tape reels (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Lloyd Hamrol and Richard Serra, 1976 April 28; 1 sound tape reels (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Introduction by Meredith Wortz.
      - Robert Irwin, 1976 May 12; 2 Sound cassettes Duplicates; 1 sound tape reels Original (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - William Moritz, 1976 May 19; 1 sound tape reels (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - What is the East? Where is the West?, 1988; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Speakers include Suzanne Muchnic, Diana Wong, Josene Starles, Carl Cheng, Joan Hugo, Daniel Wheeler, Ingird Awed, and Ann Page.
    - Light and Medium, Light as Vehicle, College Art Association, New York, N.Y., 1997; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Speakers include Susan Chorpenning, Judit Hersko, Stefan Becker, and Seth Riskin.
- Writings, 1962-1997; Series 2; 3.7 Linear feet Boxes 5-8, 16, OV 17
  This series contains handwritten and typewritten drafts, notes, research, correspondence, photographs of works of art, and other documentation related to Butterfield's book projects, articles, catalog essays, and publicity writings.
  The most extensive project in this series is Butterfield's book The Art of Light and Space, represented here in multiple drafts, galleys, photographs of works of art, editorial correspondence, records related to later exhibitions of the artists represented in the book, and records of an exhibition of artist portraits created for the book by the photographer James McHugh. Extensive files of photographs of works of art by the artists included in the book are also found in the photographs series. Note that the first two drafts in the series bear earlier titles, Context, the art of light and space, and California Light and Space, but are the same work.
  Book projects on the artists Fletcher Benton and Leonard Cutrow are also documented in this series in correspondence, business records, photographs of works of art, and scattered typescript and printout draft writings. Butterfield does not take an author credit for these projects, but she seems to have been involved in their editing and production to different degrees. A book on outdoor sculpture in San Francisco by Warren Radford is found in draft form and appears to have been edited by Butterfield. The draft is filed at the end of the series under "writings by others".
  Articles by Butterfield found in this series are mostly in the form of typescript drafts, some hand-corrected. Photocopies of Butterfield's published articles are filed with Printed Materials. Articles about artists or galleries are arranged by the subject's name. Other articles are listed in the series by title.
  Many of the files relating to catalog essays by Butterfield contain extensive documentation related to the artist subjects, including multiple drafts, photographs of works of art, and research gathered about the artist or subject matter in the form of printed materials, artist biographies and CVs from galleries, notes, and correspondence. The file for Richard Shaw also contains an interview transcript, presumably for the 1981 interview by Butterfield found In the Interviews series.
  Some of Butterfield's work as a publicist for artists and galleries is filed under publicity writings, which include drafts of press releases, exhibition reviews, photographs of artwork, research, and occasionally correspondence with the artist. A large amount of material is found related to Peter Erskine's project "Secrets of the Sun" (1992) including two videocassettes (VHS). An additional videocassette (VHS) is found with publicity writings for the artist Anne Labirola.
  Many of the writings are based on recorded interviews that can be found in series 1, Interviews and Lectures. A variety of material related to Butterfield's work on books published by Lapis Press is found in series 3, Project files, which also contains additional publicity writings by Butterfield. Extensive writings by others on the artist George Herms are found in series 4, Personal Business Records. Many of Butterfield's writings that appeared in print are found in series 5, Printed Materials. Additional photographs of works of art by the artists about whom Butterfield wrote are found in series 6, Photographs.
  - Books (Box 5)
    - The Art of Light and Space (Box 5)
      - Corrected Typescript Draft, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 5-10)
      - Typescript Draft, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11-16)
      - Typescript with Editor's Annotations, after 1988; Photocopy (Box 5, Folder 17-21)
      - Draft Fragments with Editor's Annotations (Box 6)
        - Introduction, circa 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - James Turrell Chapter, circa 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
        - DeWain Valentine Chapter, 1975, 1980, 1991; Also contains photographs, printed materials, and editorial correspondence. (Box 6, Folder 4)
          Oversized item moved to Box 16, folder 1.
        - Notes, circa 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Editorial Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Grant Proposal for Related Exhibition, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Galley Proofs, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Uncorrected Proof, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Photographs (Box 6)
        - Introductions, 1966-1981 (Box 6, Folder 10)
        - Robert Irwin, 1970-1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
        - James Turrell, 1967-1991 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
        - Maria Nordman, 1971-1983 (Box 6, Folder 14)
        - Doug Wheeler, 1967-1976 (Box 6, Folder 15)
        - Bruce Nauman, 1969-1988 (Box 6, Folder 16)
        - Eric Orr, 1968-1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
        - Larry Bell, 1965-1983 (Box 6, Folder 18)
        - DeWain Valentine, 1970-1990 (Box 6, Folder 19)
        - Susan Kaiser Vogel, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 20)
        - Hap Tivey, 1973-1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Source Material, "Robert Irwin's Theories", circa 1977 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Fletcher Benton, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Leonard Cutrow, circa 1962-1994 (Box 6, Folder 24-30)
  - Articles (Box 6)
    - Ansel Adams, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Bruce Connor, Bruce Connor Lookalike Contest and Bake Sale (1975), 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      Oversized items moved to Box 17.
    - Guy Dill, Sculpture is about Proof: The Visual Harmonics of Guy Dill, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Ferus Gallery, A Small Parenthesis in Time, circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Sam Francis, Unpublished Posthumous Article, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 35-36)
      Oversized material moved to Box 16, folder 1.
      Includes editorial correspondence in addition to writings.
    - Joe Goode, circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Robert Irwin, The Subject of Art is Aesthetic Perception, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Jasper Johns, John Cage, Merce Cunningham, The Bride and the Bachelors, circa 1977 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - The Kimball Art Museum, The Power and the Glory, circa 1972 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Pablo Picasso, The Death of a Giant, circa 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Quay Gallery and Peter Voulkos, circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Joseph Raffael, Infinite Intricateness, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "Made in America," American Art Review, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Thrills, Chills, and Spills; The Second Artists' Soapbox Derby, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Turning the Tide: Early L.A. Modernists, 1920-1956, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Catalog Essays (Box 7)
    - "Shape: Forming the L.A. Look" (1976) (Box 7)
      - Draft and Catalog, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence and Notes, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Research, circa 1991-1995 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Larry Bell, Albuquerque Museum (1997) (Box 7)
      - Draft, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence and Notes, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Research, circa 1982-1996 (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
    - Elmer Bischoff, "Walking a Tightrope," Laguna Art Museum, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Robert Hudson, "Visions of Eyes and Hands," Allan Frumkin Gallery (1976) (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Notes, circa 1976 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Early Drafts, circa 1976 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Late Drafts, circa 1976 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Research, circa 1976 (Box 7, Folder 20-21)
        Contains photocopies of articles dated 1964-1975.
    - Richard Shaw, Newport Harbor Art Museum (1981) (Box 7)
      - Drafts, circa 1981 (Box 7, Folder 22)
        Oversized material moved to Box 17.
      - Interview Transcript and Notes, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Research, circa 1976-1988 (Box 7, Folder 24)
        Oversized materials moved to Box 16, folder 1.
  - Publicity Writings (Box 7)
    - Lita Albuquerque, circa 1990-1996 (Box 7, Folder 25-26)
    - Dean Andrews, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 27-29)
    - Eleanore Berman, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Chase Chien, circa 1991 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Guy Dill, 1979-1992 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Peter Erskine, circa 1990-1992; Includes 2 videocassettes (VHS). (Box 8, Folder 1-3, Box 7, Folder 33-36)
    - Robert Irwin and James McHugh, 1991-1993 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sooja Kim, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Ann Labriola, circa 1996-1997; Includes 1 videocassette (VHS). (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Nina Frost Gallery, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tom Rose, circa 1992 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Charles Strong, 1991, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    - Joyce Treiman, 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Betty Tsou Fong, 1983, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - William Turner Gallery, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Diana Hsui-lu Wong, 1990-1994 (Box 8, Folder 15-17)
  - Writings by Others (Box 8)
    - A Heritage of Outdoor Sculpture by Warren Radford, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Space in Japanese Residential Architecture by Joseph N. Newland, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Frank Stella Chronology, circa 1987 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Item from Books, The Art of Light and Space, Draft Fragments with Editor's Annotations, DeWain Valentine Chapter (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 6, folder 4.
  - Oversized Item from Books, The Art of Light and Space, Source Material, Robert Irwin's Theories (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 6, folder 22.
  - Oversized Material from Articles, Sam Francis, Unpublishes Posthumous Article (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 6, folder 36.
  - Oversized Material from Catalog Essays, Robert Hudson, "Visions of Eyes and Hands," Research (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 7, folders 20-21.
  - Oversized Material from Catalog Essays, Richard Shaw, Newport Harbor Art Museum, Research (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Oversized materials from Box 7, folder 24.
  - Oversized Material from Articles, Bruce Connor (Box 17)
    Oversized material from Box 6, folder 32.
  - Oversized Material from Catalog Essays, Richard Shaw, Newport Harbor Art Museum, Drafts (Box 17)
    Oversized material from Box 7, folder 22.
- Project Files, circa 1950-1990; Series 3; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 8-10, 16
  This series contains records relating to major projects overseen by Butterfield, including a catalog of artworks held by the corporation Pacific Enterprises, a cross-disciplinary project overseen by Butterfield at the San Francisco Art Institute called the Waterfront Project, and a publishing company for which Butterfield served as managing editor called Lapis Press.
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries.
  3.1: The Art Collection of Pacific Enterprises Artist Files and Interviews
  3.2. Waterfront Project Photographs and Sound Recordings
  3.3. Lapis Press
  - The Art Collection of Pacific Enterprises Artist Files and Interviews, circa 1990; 3.1; 1 Linear feet (Box 8)